Today's דף ס"ד, daf samech daled, we were dealing in the משנה
mishna with the רבי ישמעאל rabbi yishmael trying to minimize the amount
of חילול שבת chilul shabbos that would be involved if you brought
the עומר omer on שבת. shabbos. And the גמרא gemara is trying
to identify other תנאים tanaim that say similar approaches that even though
you can sometimes break שבת shabbos for certain מצוות mitzvot or for
certain particularly in the בית המקדש, beit hamikdash, do we try to
do it in a way that minimizes the amount of violation? So
the גמרא gemara tries to sort of in the framework of saying
רבי ישמעאל rabbi yishmael and so and so says the same thing,
really uses it as an opportunity to say they're not exactly the
same and pointing out the different types of calculuses that could be
used to determine whether it's warranted to limit the violation of שבת
shabbos or not. So let's take a look. We pick up with
אלא, ella, five lines from the top, one, two, three, four, five,
six lines from the top, דף ס"ד עמוד א'. daf samech daled
amud alef. אלא אמר רבא, ella amar rava, rather רבא rava says
רבי ישמעאל ורבי חנינא סגן הכהנים
אמרו דבר אחד. rabbi yishmael ve'rabbi chanina sgan kohanim amru davar echad.
That really רבי ישמעאל rabbi yishmael was saying the thing the same
as רבי חנינא סגן הכהנים. rabbi chanina sgan kohanim. דתנן, demitnan, we
taught in our משנה, mishna, we taught in our משנה mishna רבי
חנניה, rabbi chananya, רבי חנינא rabbi chanina seven lines or eight lines
from the top, line starts with the word רבי חנינא. rabbi chanina.
רבי חנינא סגן הכהנים אומר בשבת נקצר ביחיד במגל אחד ובקופה אחת.
rabbi chanina sgan kohanim omer be'shabbos niktzar be'yachid be'magal echad u'be'kupa achas.
If you
when you're cutting it on שבת, shabbos, only one person does the
cutting, you use one scythe and one basket. ובחול בשלושה ובשלוש קופות
ובשלושה מגלות. u'be'chol bi'shloshah u'vi'shlosha kupot u'vi'shlosha maglot. And on the weekdays,
three people, three baskets, three scythes. וחכמים אומרים אחד בשבת ואחד בחול
בשלוש קופות ובשלושה מגלות. v'chachamim omrim echad be'shabbos ve'echad be'chol bi'shloshah kupot
u'vi'shlosha maglot. And the Rabbis say three even on שבת shabbos you
use three people and three and three scythes. So you see that
even when it's on שבת shabbos he wants to minimize the amount
of violation, even though the תורה torah gives it license to do
it on to cut the עומר omer on שבת. shabbos. So you
see it's a similar approach. מי לא אמר רבי חנינא סגן הכהנים
התם כיון דאפשר לא טרחינן? mi lo amar rabbi chanina sgan kohanim
hasam kevan de'efshar lo trachinan? So you see רבי חנינא סגן הכהנים
rabbi chanina sgan kohanim says since it's possible to do it with
fewer people, we will do it with fewer people and we will
not violate שבת shabbos as much even though it requires
so therefore הכא נמי hacha nami so here too כיון דאפשר kevan
de'efshar because it's possible to do with less violation that you do
it with only three סאה seah and not five סאה seah that
you cut in order to get what the requisite amount of flour
you need for the עומר, omer, לא טרחינן lo trachinan you also
would not do that effort and do it more. Now it's interesting
the גמרא gemara uses the phrase לא טרחינן lo trachinan because the
problem really isn't טרחה, tircha, the problem really is the degree of
חילול שבת chilul shabbos that's occurring. You know, it might actually be
less טרחה tircha to use more people, less טרחה tircha to cut
more wheat and then process it all more easily. So the phrase
לא טרחינן lo trachinan is strange, but obviously the point is that
we try to minimize the amount of חילול שבת, chilul shabbos, that's
what רבי ישמעאל rabbi yishmael says and similarly it seems to be
what רבי חנינא סגן הכהנים rabbi chanina sgan kohanim is saying each
at different stages. רבי ישמעאל rabbi yishmael in terms of how much
wheat was cut and רבי חנינא סגן הכהנים rabbi chanina sgan kohanim
in terms of how many people were involved.
This is a little bit difference than what we usually see of
like ריבוי עבירות בהעלם אחד. ribuyei aveiros be'helem echad. Yep. If you
were to do five סאה seah worth or three סאה seah worth,
the שוגג shogeg it's the same חטאת, chatas, right? You're not more
culpable.
Oh hold on a second. I think I just you might have
audio now. Okay. I'm sorry, go on one more time.
Yeah. In when for example if you do קמתם בשוגג בהעלם אחד.
kamtum b'shogeg be'helem echad. Yeah. If it's no difference if you do
five סאות seahs worth or three סאות seahs worth, you're still חייב
chayav only one חטאת, chatas, it's not considered...
Right. Well, it is true that a שיעור shiur and we're going
to see that later, that what degree do you consider if you
do multiple a larger שיעור shiur have you done multiple sins or
basically it's just one sin once you hit the minimum. Here though,
it's not בשוגג be'shogeg and it is true that if I say
the famous example of a נזיר nazir that was שותה יין כל
היום, shoteh yayin kol hayom, if you warn him once he gets
one set of מלקות, malkus, if you warn him before each שיעור
shiur he gets multiple sets of מלקויות. malkuyos. So the continued eating
could be just seen as one act or could be seen as
multiple acts and somehow it's redefined it could be defined differently based
on whether it's התראה hasra'ah or other types of formal ways to
define it. So it does seem that could be part of the
חשבון cheshbon the גמרא gemara had which says we'd rather you do
more sifting and less cutting because less cutting means like you're going
over to different grain and you're cutting maybe conceptually that's easier to
see that as a separate חילול chilul where this is just a
continuation. Whether formally or not it's one or it's multiple violations is
hard to exactly gauge. Again because what you have when you do
it במזיד be'mazid that it depends whether we הלכה halachically give you
multiple מלקויות malkuyos or just one depends on the התראה hasra'ah but
then it's unclear is the התראה hasra'ah a sin of מלקות malkus
or it's a sin in really seeing it as single or multiple
violations. But you are right and we're going to see that more
later in the גמרא gemara that the גמרא gemara is going to
give an example which really gets this to the essence where you
could do a bigger שיעור shiur and fewer acts or smaller שיעור
shiur in more acts. So hold off on that till we see
the end of the גמרא. gemara. Okay, so now the גמרא gemara
says the following.
Okay, so where were we?
Okay so the גמרא gemara says בשלושה מגלות. bi'shlosha maglot. מי לא
אמר? mi lo amar? ממאי mimai how do you know that that's
really what they're saying the exact same thing? דילמא dilma maybe we'd
say עד כאן לא אמר רבי ישמעאל הכא אלא דליכא פרסומי מילתא.
ad kan lo amar rabbi yishmael hacha ela deleka pirsumei milsa. I
almost said מיתה. misa.
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael only said that I want to minimize it
if there is not another benefit. If I have the benefit might
be that if when you're in the cutting, the more people you
use, the more it makes a whole public event out of it.
And particularly by the עומר, Omer, which is an importance to make
it a public event because of the צדוקים. Tzedukim. Now the fact
that we're going to start to think about our general sort of,
you know, fight with the צדוקים Tzedukim and trying to make this
sort of, you know, big public event and that that would warrant
more חילול שבת, Chilul Shabbos, חילול שבת. Chilul Shabbos. No no no.
Think that when I have the benefit of פרסומי מלתא, pirsumei milsa,
maybe רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael would say that I would say to
do it with more people.
בעין, be'in, because I understand that's a הוה אמינא. havaminah.
No, not the הוה אמינא. havaminah. Just as רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
says you use you do less of a חילול שבת Chilul Shabbos
when you're doing the sifting, he might say you do a more
when you're doing the cutting because he might do it for the
sake of the gain of the פרסומי מלתא, pirsumei milsa, which is
interesting because it would seem that the issue of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael to minimize the חילול שבת Chilul Shabbos would be a דאורייתא
d'oraisa concern, like a type of
הותרה, דחויה. hutra d'chuyah Yes, you're allowed to do it, but you
have to do it in the way that at most minimizes it.
If so, it's a little bit funny that the value of פרסומי
מלתא pirsumei milsa and making a point against the
צדוקים Tzedukim would weigh into an allowance. However, you could say no,
first of all you could certainly say that it's a religious gain
in order to, you know, make the הלכה Halacha clear in general,
so it serves religious ends, it's not obviously political, and maybe even
more so specifically about when it comes to ספירה Sefira and the
עומר Omer and שבועות, Shavuos, the whole idea is וספרתם לכם ממחרת
השבת u'sefartem lachem mimacharas hashabbos and you have to declare and there's
actually a מצווה mitzvah to, you know, do the whole counting up
and the declaring. So there there's like a direct sort of... and
the עומר Omer begins that process. You could sort of see that
making it clear that this is the day that the counting begins
is very connected to the מצווה mitzvah of the עומר Omer and
the מצווה mitzvah of counting. It is a little ironic we should
say that one of the few times the תורה Torah says that
there's a whole big deal about actually,
you know, dedicating the day, acknowledging the day, counting from the day
is exactly the one that is so disputed when exactly that day
is and how that counting takes place. But my point is you
could see the פרסומי מלתא pirsumei milsa is not just like, you
know, making a point against the צדוקים, Tzedukim, it's actually part very
much connected to the מצווה mitzvah of the עומר. Omer. Yes, Mordechai?
I was just going to tie into that and especially if we
say too the reason why this could be a דחויה שבת d'chuya
Shabbos is because it, you know, from a פסוק pasuk telling us
that we have to do it, when the פסוק pasuk is ממחרת
השבת. mimacharas hashabbos.
Extra strong point.
Right, right, so how much more so do we need to make
the point? Right, the question is that if it's a דאורייתא d'oraisa
issue what we, you know, how do we calculate what that sort
of value is to make that point? And I would say דווקא
davka because the מצווה ספירה mitzvah Sefira might be saying sort of,
you know, you have to make it clear how you're leading up
to this day and dedicating this day and so on. Okay, so
that's what he says. So maybe רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael would agree
that when it comes to the cutting you use more people for
the sake of פרסומי מלתא. pirsumei milsa. ולימא כרבנן סבירא ליה?
ve'leima
kerabbanan sevira leh?
One minute, maybe you would say like the רבנן Rabbanan that say
that we do we do three people and we make a bigger
deal about it. Or the reverse, אי נמי אכתי לא קאמר רבי
חנינא סגן הכהנים התם דבחד דבשלשה צורך גבוה מתעבד. i nami achati
lo ka'amar Rabbi Chanina Sgan Hakohanim hatam d'b'chad d'b'shlasha tzorech gavoah mi'avid.
Or when רבי חנינא סגן הכהנים Rabbi Chanina Sgan Hakohanim says use
one, that's because using one or using three does not cut down
your end result, does not impact how much you're satisfying what the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash needs are, right? If you use one person
you're going to get the exact same end result, it's just going
to take you three times as much time. But there's no impact
about what the צורך גבוה, tzorech gavoah, how you're affecting the בית
המקדש'ס Beis Hamikdash's interests, right, כהלכתו. ke'hilchaso.
You're doing the תורה'ס, Torah's, God's needs appropriately. אבל הכא, aval hacha,
but here when you do שלש סאין shalosh se'in and not חמש
סאין, chamesh se'in, דלא קעביד כהלכתו, de'lo qabid ke-hilchaso, you're not doing
as ideally what the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash needs are. ולימא כרבנן
סבירא ליה? ve'leima kerabbanan sevira leh? Maybe he would hold like the
רבנן. Rabbanan. Meaning, if you feel that חמש סאין chamesh se'in is
the ideal, it's interesting, the רבנן Rabbanan actually held שלש סאין shalosh
se'in is fine, but if you hold like רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
that חמש סאין chamesh se'in is the ideal, what you're saying is
the flour that you get out of חמש סאין, chamesh se'in, and
the גמרא Gemara wasn't so clear about this, at one point the
גמרא Gemara made it sound like it was a question of more
or less effort. It's easier to get fine flour out of חמש
סאין, chamesh se'in, takes a lot more effort to get it out
of שלש סאין. shalosh se'in. But presumably there's another point too, if
you start with a much larger quantity then you can have a
much finer sifting and you can get finer flour. If you have
to really work to get the flour out of שלש סאין, shalosh
se'in, the flour won't be as fine. That seems to be what's
informing the גמרא Gemara here. So therefore maybe רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina
would say I'm willing to do one person if it's because in
the end the result will be the same, it just takes that
one guy three times as long, but the result will be the
same. But if that's actually going to impact the result, then I'm
going to want to do it at a bigger scale. So the
גמרא Gemara is by doing these comparison contrasts, they're pointing out all
the different types of calculuses you could use, you know, to determine
if we want to minimize the חילול שבת Chilul Shabbos even when
warranted, but what other values are at play and do we is
it always right to completely minimize the חילול שבת? Chilul Shabbos? You
had a question.
No, I was just saying, so in the end we don't know,
like, you know, how many people רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says to
use and we can't necessarily figure it out.
Exactly, we know what he said about one thing, we don't know
what he would say about the other.
And the same thing with רבי חנינא. Rabbi Chanina. Exactly. Alright, that's
what we're left with.
Yeah, but we're doing it as like... but when we say דבר
אחד, davar achad, we're not saying they פסקן pasken the same, I
mean we are in a way, but what we're really trying to
say is they have the exact same position about
minimizing. how they apply that might vary differently from case to case.
Okay, so the גמרא's Gemara going to continue in this vein for
a bit.
Okay, אלא אמר רב אשי, Ella amar Rav Ashi, so rather רב
אשי Rav Ashi says it's like this. אלא אמר, Ella amar, like
we're trying very hard to find a way to find who רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael can partner with in his exact position. רבי ישמעאל
ורבי יוסי אמרו דבר אחד, Rabbi Ishmael v'Rabbi Yosi amru davar echad,
Rabbi Ishmael and Rabbi Yosi say the same thing. דתנן, Detnan, we
taught in the משנה, Mishnah, בין שנראה בעליה ובין שלא נראה
בעליה, bein she-nira ba'aliya u-vein shelo nira ba'aliya, there's seeing the new
moon and coming to בית דין Beis Din to testify and you
can violate שבת Shabbos to come to בית דין Beis Din to
testify that you saw the new moon. So whether it was seen
בעליה, ba'aliya, like clearly, or whether it was seen שלא נראה בעליה,
shelo nira ba'aliya, it wasn't seen clearly, it was seen on a
cloudy night and you were very lucky to get a glimpse of
it, you know, as opposed to it was a clear night and
you could assume that everybody in the country saw the new moon.
That's נראה בעליה. nira ba'aliya. שלא נראה בעליה shelo nira ba'aliya is
that it was cloudy, it wasn't so clear that people saw it,
you were fortunate enough to see it. Either case, מחללים עליו את
השבת, mechallelin alav es haShabbos, you would violate שבת Shabbos if you
had to in order to get to ירושלים Yerushalayim to testify that
you saw the new moon, to establish when ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh
is.
If you're far away there you're just like running so you're riding...
Yeah, you're riding on a
horse bypass the תחום techum of people not going beyond the תחום.
techum.
No, no, no, no, that you would violate for the sake of
being the witness to testify. We're not talking about proclaiming the moon,
we're talking about testifying. To testify you have to show up in
person. Okay, so you would violate שבת, Shabbos, you'd get on a
if you needed a horse to get there on time, if you
were a sick person and you needed to people, you know, to
carry a bed or different kinds of things, you would do what
you had to do to get there to testify on time.
But didn't they light torches?
That was to proclaim it, that was going in the opposite direction.
That once it was dedicated to proclaim.
But they didn't do that on שבת. Shabbos.
And that they didn't do on שבת, Shabbos, the lighting of the
torches. But to dedicate it, if you miss the day then you're
not going to make today ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. That's why there's
an urgency to do it today. You could proclaim today or tomorrow,
but there's an urgency to do it on the day you saw
it because if you come a day later then today doesn't become
ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh.
But the people in the other communities then would not know.
What would they need to do? They don't need to know other
than ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, what do they care about ראש חודש?
Rosh Chodesh?
How will they know today? They see it the next night when
it was
oh
I see oh I see
your question is is that whether how do they know what the
torches are communicating. They must have had a system. Okay, you know
what, that's a great question they did right that's a great question
they must have had a system. I mean it could be that
like you would you would do torches, you know, which would indicate
that the previous month was maybe חסר chaser or מלא malei with
how the torches indicated what day it was you know the day
itself. It's a good question but I'm sure they had a system,
I'm sure they had it figured out. Right, okay you do two
torches, three torches. Okay anyway so the תנא Tanna says like this.
Okay so either way you're מחלל שבת. mechalel Shabbos. רבי יוסי אומר
אם נראה בעליה אין מחללים עליו את השבת. Rabbi Yosi omer im
nira ba'aliya ein mechallelin alav es haShabbos. If it was seen clearly
don't be מחלל שבת. mechalel Shabbos. We can assume that tons of
people saw it and who needs you to violate שבת Shabbos to
come to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash to testify. מי איכא, Mi
ika, so you see, מי לא אמר רבי יוסי התם כיון דאפשר
לא טרחינן, mi lo amar Rabbi Yosi hatam keivan de-efshar lo tarchinan,
since you see Rabbi Yosi said since it's possible to achieve that
result without your violation of שבת, Shabbos, we don't do the effort.
Again the phrase is effort is a very funny one but we
don't do that activity maybe would be the best thing, as it's
not needed. הכא נמי, Hacha nami, here too by the חמש סאה,
chamesh se'ah, כיון דאפשר לא טרחינן, keivan de-efshar lo tarchinan, because it's
possible we don't do that activity of doing the more grain, we
do the lesser grain because it can achieve the same result and
we don't do more violation of שבת. Shabbos. So it goes ממאי,
mi-mai, how do you know it's the exact same? דאי אמרת עד
כאן לא קאמר רבי ישמעאל הכא אלא דליכא נפקא מינה למילתא דלמחר,
De-i amrat ad kan lo ka'amar Rabbi Yishmael hacha ella delika nafka
mina lemilsa delmachar, when does again
there's other values at stake, there's other concerns at stake. When does
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael say I want you to do only three
סאה se'ah not five, that there's not some other concern. What's the
other concern? So the same way before the other concern was we
wanted to publicize it, here by ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh the other
concern is that if you send people back and you say oh
you know what you shouldn't have come, it was so clear and
I don't want you to come so a that's not sending it
back but let's say sending telling them at the outset not to
come. If it's very clear I don't want you to come and
if you did show up and you violated שבת Shabbos I'll say
to you why'd you violate שבת? Shabbos? It was so clear everybody
would have seen it. Next time don't do that. What's going to
happen? Next time I'm going to see it and I'm going to
say to myself they probably aren't going to want me to come
on שבת, Shabbos, you know it was a little cloudy but I'm
sure other people saw it, I'm not going to bother. And in
the end you were the one person who because of you we
could have made it a ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh but you assumed
we wouldn't want you to come because it was שבת. Shabbos. So
you don't want people to be too פרום frum about this because
then they will not come on שבת Shabbos when we really need
them. So that is a, you know, a counterbalancing concern to we
don't want to have too much חילול שבת. chillul Shabbos. So maybe
although רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael minimizes the חילול שבת chillul Shabbos here,
there he would say we tell everybody to come regardless because we
don't want it in the future to lead to such people not
showing up. Okay, so that's why he would say there maybe he
would tell people to come.
אבל התם, Aval hatam, over there, דנמצאת אתה מכשילו לעתיד לבוא, de-nimzes
ata machshilo le-asid lavo, if you send them back or tell them
not to come, you'll trip them up for the future, they won't
come when you needed them to come. אימא כרבנן סבירא ליה, Eima
ke-Rabbanan sevira leh, maybe he holds like the רבנן Rabbanan that even
if the moon was seen very clearly we tell אי נמי Inami
or alternatively התם לא קאמר רבי יוסי
התם hatam lo ka'amar Rabbi Yosi hasam וליכא צורך גבוה v'leika tzorech
gavoah over there רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi only said it because there
was why did רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi say that don't come because
who needs you your coming is not going to help make it
any better for the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash assuming that it was
seen clearly your coming is completely unnecessary it's not serving צורך גבוה
tzorech gavoah the needs of God the needs of religious needs at
least not immediately ולא ניתנה שבת להידחות v'lo nitna Shabbos lidechos and
therefore there's no justification to violate שבת Shabbos אבל הכא דאיכא צורך
גבוה aval hacha de'ika tzorech gavoah here that the needs of the
temple are served better when you do five סאה se'ah because presumably
the grain is the flour is a finer flour so here where
the needs of the temple are served better ניתנה שבת להידחות nitna
Shabbos lidechos and we are allowed to violate שבת Shabbos at the
outset meaning we're violating שבת Shabbos for the three סאה se'ah אימא
כרבנן סבירא ליה eima kerabbanan sevira leh it'll be like the rabbis
so the difference there is Michael saw it on a beautiful day
so who needs Michael to violate שבת Shabbos other people saw it
Michael's coming is not going to help us and as far as
Michael is concerned he hasn't even started violating שבת Shabbos why should
he jump into a car to drive to the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash right other people can do it he's out of the picture
so therefore that's we could say that's why רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi
would say Michael don't come but when it comes to doing five
סאה se'ah opposed to three סאה se'ah רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi could
say look you're already in the middle of cutting down three סאה
se'ah so you're already you are already Michael here's the guys who's
out there in the field cutting it down you're already violating שבת
Shabbos for the קצירה ketzira of the עומר Omer so you're not
out of the picture you're in the picture ניתנה שבת להידחות nitna
Shabbos lidechos and now the question is three or five would they
do more because the more you do the better the flour will
have in the end result and it does help serve our end
result better so again there's a different calculus in each case it
is quite fascinating again whether this concern is a seen as a
דאורייתא De'Oraisa concern or a דרבנן De'Rabbanan concern if it's a דאורייתא
De'Oraisa concern a type of a דחויה ולא הותרה d'chuyah v'lo hutra
and you can only violate you know exactly as much as is
warranted then it's fascinating that what types of different sort of חשבונות
cheshbonos and factors go into this question of what is warranted you
know what is warranted what type of policies and considerations do you
ask in terms of this question of what is warranted and that's
why the גמרא Gemara says you could have agree in principle but
have a lot of different end
results
yeah how much these principles are transferable to other discussions of problems
of the common by שבת Shabbos in the Manhattan scenario and we're
out you know in the middle of Manhattan we see an accident
happen on שבת Shabbos then I'm trying to figure out now do
I flip the phone and call an ambulance right
so by פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh so that's a very good point
to contrast you know on the one hand I would say that
sometimes by פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh you know people sort of feel
once it's ניתנה שבת להידחות nitna Shabbos lidechos I mean that's one
of the points the גמרא Gemara made Michael already started cutting down
the three סאה se'ah then it's a different thing to say continue
the five than if who needs to drive to come to to
be מעיד ma'id if a hundred other people are coming to be
מעיד ma'id okay so but that as a psychological
reality ניתנה שבת להידחות nitna Shabbos lidechos plays out sometimes you know
when doctors go to a hospital and they basically act like non-שבת
Shabbos rather than really sort of making חשבונות cheshbonos and I'm not
saying that a lot of those decisions are not warranted in order
to you know for פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh concerns but sometimes it
it does psychologically become like oh I'm a doctor in a hospital
now and it's like שבת Shabbos doesn't exist anymore and that's not
halachically correct so that just as like a mentality of the הותרה
hutra, on the other hand the point you say this הותרה hutra
דחויה d'chuya. types of considerations never apply by פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh
for the גמרא Gemara is extremely clear by פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh
you know that you know don't hesitate do everything you need to
do you know obviously we don't want to do anything that might
compromise addressing פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh concerns and we're actually going to
see something very similar exactly on that point at the bottom of
the דף daf so it's good that you raise it but I
would say you know exactly as the גמרא Gemara sort of pointing
out there could be different here the גמרא Gemara saying we're going
to work with an assumption essentially of דחויה d'chuyah of minimizing it
but minimizing it you know as it you know not doing more
than necessary and the difference would be what defines necessary but your
issue of קדושת שבת kedushas Shabbos is important because sometimes it's not
דחויה d'chuyah sometimes it's הותרה hutra sometimes the whole point is you
know don't make any חשבונות cheshbonos or you might want to say
it slightly different way even if it's true that by פיקוח נפש
pikuach nefesh it's דחויה d'chuyah but what is necessary by פיקוח נפש
pikuach nefesh always includes anything that might lead to a possible risk
of this person's life so therefore you know anybody doing anything even
if you think other people are doing it is included in what
is necessary by פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh but it's a very good
point to raise
then you see an accident and you look around and there's forty
people there and you see several on their cell phones you still
find out
that's you know again that's when it's clearly not necessary I don't
think I don't know that's a good question let's hold off at
least until we get to the bottom of the page you know
I would say there's a slightest ספק safek that you have in
your head like oh yeah I know you know I know I
have my friend the doctor they're calling their friends the doctors I'm
calling my friends the doctors my friend the doctor might pick up
and their friends the doctors might not then you get on your
cell phone if everybody is calling 911 and five people have already
dialed 911 there's no point for you to dial 911 okay so
there's a little
bit
of a soft edge out there of you
know the boundary of the the I'm saying like there part of
the issue is you don't know what's going to happen when they
show up and you know so there are yeah sometimes if it's
100% superfluous then don't do it. That's what I'll say. All right,
let's go on.
Okay okay fine. So איתמר. itmar. So now that we're on this
topic, so we've done sort of showing different opinions along the along
the range about this. Now we're going to continue in some of
these types of issues about violating שבת. Shabbos. Let's take a look.
שחט שתי חטאות של ציבור ואינו צריך אלא לאחת. shachas shtei chataos
shel tzibur ve'eino tzarich ela le'achas. So a person slaughtered two sin
offerings of the ציבור, tzibur, it was מוסף, musaf, it was a
יום טוב Yom Tov that fell on שבת, Shabbos, so it was
a שעיר לחטאת. se'ir lachattas.
And this person accidentally slaughtered two animals for the חטאת, chattas, he
only needs one. According to one lesson, Rashi sounds almost like the
other one was also לחטאת ציבור, lachattas tzibur, but not one that
should have been brought for today. Like, let's say it was the
שעיר לעבודה זרה se'ir l'avodah zarah that we were waiting until Sunday
to bring or something, you know, for the whole ציבור tzibur sin
by עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. But it doesn't matter, one of them
is clearly the קרבן korban to be brought today and the other
is not. This isn't the case where it's
lost and you found
it, we're not dealing with that. And you accidentally slaughtered both of
them on שבת. Shabbos. You were only supposed to slaughter the one
that was the מוסף. musaf. ואינו צריך אלא לאחת, ve'eino tzarich ela
le'achas, so אמר רבא ואיתימא רבי אמי, amar Rava ve'iseima Rabbi Ami,
so Rava or some say Rabbi Ami says, חייב על השניה פטור
על הראשונה. chayav al hashniya patur al harishona.
You transgress for the second one, you were מחלל שבת mechallel Shabbos
without a justification. You had already brought your קרבן מוסף. korban musaf.
Again, if you did it בשוגג, beshogeg, then okay, you did it
בשוגג, beshogeg, nobody's going to stone you. You need another one of
those? You bring your קרבן korban as a חטאת, chattas, you bring
a קרבן korban as a חטאת, chattas, but you now violated שבת
Shabbos without justification. And for the first one, of course, you're יוצא
yotzei because they're not just פטור, patur, you were יוצא. yotzei. ואפילו
נתכפר לו בשניה. ve'afillu nitkaper lo bashniya.
And not only that, it all is determined by the moment that
you did the slaughtering. So if you slaughtered the first one and
then you slaughtered the second, and then the blood of the first
one spilled, let's say, and then you wound up using the second
one as your קרבן, korban, it doesn't matter. You still were מחלל
שבת mechallel Shabbos at the moment you slaughtered the second. It's true
that now in hindsight you were justified in doing it, but at
the moment you were not. So if you slaughtered the first one,
you spilled the blood, then we would tell you slaughter the second
one. But if you slaughtered the first one, slaughtered the second one,
and then spilled the blood of the first one, you'd already had
violated שבת Shabbos when you slaughtered the second. We don't reassess based
on hindsight. Okay, that's what he says. ואפילו נתכפר לו בשניה. ve'afillu
niskaper lo bashniya. And not only that, ואפילו נמצאת ראשונה כחושה. ve'afillu
nimsatz rishona kachusha. Even if the first one, after you slaughtered it,
you said, you know, this is a scrawny goat, maybe we should
bring a nicer goat, and then you brought the nicer one, you're
still not you're violating שבת Shabbos because you already could have used
the first one. Okay, so you are violated... I'm sorry, you are
violating שבת Shabbos that you're no longer allowed to violate שבת. Shabbos.
You already can use the first one, even if it's כחושה, kachusha,
and therefore bringing the second one you would violate. So the גמרא
Gemara is going to be interested in this case about כחושה. kachusha.
ומי אמר רבא הכי? umi amar Rava hachi? Did Rava really say
that?
והאמר רבא, veha'amar Rava, didn't Rava say, היו לפניו שתי חטאות? hayu
lefanav shtei chataos? You had in front of him two sin offerings
on יום טוב Yom Tov let's say on שבת, Shabbos, אחת שמנה
ואחת כחושה, achas shmena ve'achas kachusha, one fat and good, the other
thin, skinny, and scrawny like
פרעה. Paroh. שחט שמנה ואחר כחושה, shachas shmena ve'achar kachusha, so if
you slaughtered the first one and then the scrawny one, again, you
were only supposed to slaughter one, it was שבת Shabbos and you
only had one שעיר לחטאת. se'ir lachattas. חייב, chayav, then you're חייב
chayav because you violated שבת Shabbos when you slaughtered the second. However,
כחושה ואחר שמנה, kachusha ve'achar shmena, if you slaughtered the scrawny one
and then the nice fat one, פטור, patur, you're exempt. Why? ולא
עוד, velo od, even more than that, אלא שאומרים לו, ella she'omrim
lo, if you slaughtered the first one it was scrawny, and then
you said you turned to your fellow כהנים kohanim and he said,
hey guys, this is a real scrawny חטאת chattas to bring for
מוסף musaf or for סוכות Sukkos or whatever it is, so אומרים
לו, omrim lo, הביא שמנה לכתחילה ושחוט. havei shmena l'chatchila ushchos. So
here's an amazing idea about how שבת Shabbos overrides, you know, how
bringing קרבנות korbanos overrides שבת Shabbos in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
that even if you slaughtered it and I now could satisfy my
obligation of the חטאת chattas by sprinkling the blood, if it's not
the ideal קרבן, korban, it's כשר, kosher, it's not ideal, it was
כחושה, kachusha, it wasn't nice and fat or whatever, I'm allowed to
go ahead and violate שבת Shabbos again in order to bring a
nicer קרבן. korban. So that's an amazing question, you know, what are
the parameters about what is how you can violate? So here we're
finding out that you violate שבת Shabbos to bring the necessary קרבנות
korbanos and to bring them in the ideal way. So if I
even if it now will require a separate act of שחיטה, shechita,
if that'll make a nicer קרבן, korban, I'm allowed to violate that.
That's what Rava says. So clearly if Rava will let you do
it לכתחילה, l'chatchila, he's not going to say you're חייב chayav if
you actually went ahead and slaughtered the scrawny one and then the
nice...
wait a minute, even though he slaughtered it, they're still saying,
אומרים לו הביא שמנה ושחוט. omrim lo havei shmena ushchos. That is
enough to to you are justified to to violate שבת Shabbos in
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash to bring the קרבנות היום, korbanos hayom,
not only what is not only what is minimally required to bring
the קרבנות היום, korbanos hayom, but even if you could have already
brought it and now you
have... well, you didn't sprinkle
the
blood
yet.
If you sprinkled the blood... So why not do five then?
You know, you are saying... Okay, hold on, let's get back to
your... Let's finish the
גמרא's Gemara thought. Finish the גמרא's Gemara thought. So the גמרא Gemara
says איבעית אימא שמינה כחושה מקמייתא. Iba'is eima shemeina kshusha mikamyaisa. So
the גמרא Gemara says you're right. קונטרס Kuntres said that you're חייב
chayav if you slaughtered the scrawny one first, he allows you לכתחילה
lechatchila to do the fat one. So either cross out the אפילו
שמינה ואפילו כחושה afilu shemeina v'afilu kshusha in the first statement of
רבא. Raba. You'll have to cross it out, take it out. ואיבעית
אימא V'iba'is eima or he רבי אמי אמר. Rebbi Ami amar. If
you remember it said either רבי אמי Rebbi Ami and some say
רבא Raba said the following. So now we know, it wasn't רבא,
Raba, it was רבי אמי Rebbi Ami because רבא Raba clearly says
it's allowed. So here you have that רבא Raba actually allows you
in retrospect if you needed to do it, it's not enough. It
has to be you needed to do it at the moment. Okay,
so if in the end it worked out you didn't bring the
first one, it doesn't save you from having violated שבת Shabbos with
the second. Retrospect doesn't help. But if it's if רבא Raba is
saying, you know, not everybody agrees, רבא's Raba saying it's you can
violate שבת Shabbos to make it nicer. So Michael asks a good
question, which is, you know, why does... רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon doesn't
have to do with רבא Raba anyway, it's a question on רבא
Raba not on anybody else. You know, but רבא Raba could say
he holds like the רבנן. Rabbanan. But Michael is making a good
point, not to say the קשיא kasha but to just say, you
know, isn't this implicitly, doesn't רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon implicitly not say
this? Because רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is basically here you could violate
שבת, Shabbos, make it a nicer, isn't a שמינה shemeina like cleaner
flour, the analogy to a שמינה? shemeina? I see you make a
very good point. You're right. It seems like... I hadn't thought of
that, but you're right. It seems like רבא Raba is really in
contrast to רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, yes.
But what do you do if the wheat is not acceptable? Could
you use it for something else? But once it's קרבן אשם, korban
asham, what could you do with the first קרבן korban if you
don't give it?
You're right, you can't do anything with it. You'd have to burn
and let it destroy. So that's another חידוש, chiddush, which is that
for the sake of making this the קרבן korban nicer, even if
the consequence means getting rid of, you know, in a way you
could say forget שבת, Shabbos, right? Maybe I shouldn't be allowed to
throw out this
קרבן korban for the sake of now just bringing, you know, doing
a do-over and making it better. I think that's a very good
point. That רבא's Raba position is a big חידוש, chiddush, you're right.
It's not just that it's warranted to violate שבת Shabbos for that
sake, but you actually can discard what otherwise would have been a
good קרבן korban and basically, you know, burn it and destroy it.
You make a very good point. רבא's Raba definitely a very big
חידוש, chiddush, yes.
Yeah, I'm very disturbed by this because I think we've crossed over
the idea that a קרבן korban is for our need and now
we're saying God really wants fatter meat. Don't give God a scrawny
little thing, God... And the same with the flour, don't give God...
if you can give... God needs...
Well, okay, but let me just...
Again, I don't know if גבוה, Gavoha, like I mean, God needs
it as much as it's serving a religious goal. Let me ask
you the following question. Why should I waste good money on buying
a nicer אתרוג? esrog? Why not just give that money to צדקה?
tzedakah? Why should I waste good money on any הידור מצווה? hiddur
mitzvah? If it's all for me and not for God, I can
do without the nicer אתרוג. esrog. Why should I spend money on
any הידור מצווה? hiddur mitzvah?
An animal's life that's totally wasted. You're taking... you're saying...
Right, I get
it.
But that's not the point that our needs or God's needs... Okay,
but that I get, and that's a... and that's the... right, that's
the moral variation of... right, that's the moral variation of what was
just asked, but it's not like any time to do it nicer
is like God, I, God needs it to be nicer. I mean,
you know, you could argue about a religious value in making things
nicer without focusing on God's needs. Okay.
That's when you're selecting the best from everything in front of you
is one thing, but here you've already chosen something and now you
see something else better, so you're wasting...
Right, so that's the moral objection. Right, so I understand. That's so
like the moral objection to what, you know, to what רבא Raba
is saying. On the one hand, just in terms of the respect
of קדשים, kodshim, you know, not even bringing morality into it, just
respect of קדשים, kodshim, is sort of making a nicer
קרבן korban justify, you know, taking this קרבן korban in front of
you and letting it become פסול? posul? And you're sort of raising
it from the moral perspective, right? Just making something nicer, how does
that justify the type of waste of resources and waste of life?
Yeah, those are all very good questions. I don't have an answer.
But what I'm saying is that the thought seems to have passed,
crossed the boundary of what we have a need to give something...
I don't see that... I would frame the question differently. I don't
see... Meaning, you're saying that the only way that you could understand
why we would say override these other concerns is if we framed
it as God really needs it.
Whatever, we're
saying this religious value overrides other types of concerns, but to still
say, but why is it? Why is the religious value of הידור
מצוה mitzvah. *hidur mitzvah* override these important other considerations? The moral issues,
the issues of wasting a קרבן korban *korban* and so on. So
either way it's a question, and I hear it's a very good
question. Okay, let's continue. So הגמרא *ha-gemara* says like this. אמר ליה
amar lei, רבינא לרב אשי *amar leih Ravina le-Rav Ashi*. So Ravina
asked that question I said
about is it Rabbi Yishmael was disagreeing with him?
No, it's a very good point. הגמרא *ha-gemara* does not ask it.
אמר ליה *amar leih* or does not address it. It's not a
question. הגמרא *ha-gemara* does not address it? I haven't seen it, but
I mean I have תוספות *Tosafot* open. I'll have to look. אמר
ליה רבינא לרב אשי *amar leih Ravina le-Rav Ashi*. So Ravina said
to Rav Ashi: נמצאת הראשונה כחושה kechusha בבני מעיים מהו *nimtzet ha-rishona
k'husha b'vnei mei'ayim mahu*?
Now here, Rifka, you can get even more offended. He says, let's
say the second one was scrawny, but it was only discovered to
be scrawny when you actually got to cutting it up and taking
out the innards. Now רש"י *Rashi* is a little bit unclear what
this means, when you actually started looking at it closely, you saw,
oh my god, its bones are sticking out, it looks so scrawny,
I wasn't paying attention when I checked it. But more literally, נמצאת
כחושה kechusha בבני מעיים *nimtzet k'husha b'vnei mei'ayim*, the liver doesn't look
too good. The liver that I'm going to put on the מזבח
*mizbeach* is a small
liver, and the small intestine or whatever, this fat, not so much
fat, I don't have so much fat to put on the מזבח
*mizbeach*. So it's not even sort of the moment of slaughtering it
should look
nice, it's the what's the fattiness, the שמנא *shmeina* is a facet
put on the מזבח *mizbeach*. So let's say you've only discovered that.
So first of all, there's an assumption that that's also a concern
of nicer קרבן korban? *korban* is nicer fat to put on the
מזבח *mizbeach*. So that's only discovered after slaughter. Okay. So now, why
should that matter? Again, the question here is that you slaughtered it,
it looked good. Then you slaughtered another one. So, oh, you slaughtered
it with a, you saw another one, you were violating שבת Shabbos,
*Shabbat*. Okay. Then afterwards, you found out that the first one wasn't
so good. So it's really very similar to the question before. In
retrospect, your second one was justified, but at the moment you did
it, it had not been justified. You didn't realize the first one
was scrawny. So what's the הלכה *halakha*? So the answer seems like
it'll be obvious, let's take a look.
מהו *mahu*? בתר מחשבה אזלינן *batar machshava azlinan*, do we go by
what was in your head? דגברא איסורא קא מכווין *de-gavra issura ka
michavein*, and you were intending to do an איסור *issur*. Now רש"י
*Rashi* is quick to point out no, you didn't really want to
do an איסור *issur*, you're a nice guy, you're trying to bring
a קרבן korban *korban*, but what it means is you, in your
head, you were not justified, you did not have an override to
bring the second one. You had already a first one was slaughtered,
you were making some mistake, you thought somehow it was allowed to
bring this second קרבן korban *korban* on שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*, but that
was your error, okay? And therefore, you subjectively were not aware, did
not have
a justified override to bring this, to bring this second קרבן korban,
*korban*. So therefore, you violate. או דילמא *o dilma*, or do we
say, בתר מעשה ma'aseh אזלינן *batar ma'aseh azlinan*? We don't look about
what was in your head, we look at objectively what was true
about the act. And that act actually at the time was justified.
Now this is why it's better than spilling the blood, okay? Because
spilling the blood is totally retrospect. Here's the difference between objective and
subjective. What do I mean? If I slaughter the first one, let's
forget fat and skinny, they're both lovely. I slaughter the first one,
then I slaughter the second one, then I spill the blood of
the first. So now in retrospect I needed the second one, slaughtering
was needed, but it doesn't matter, at the time it was completely
unnecessary. At the time the blood had not yet been
spilled. In this case, I slaughter the first one, I slaughter the
second one. At the time it is justified because the first one
is scrawny, the scrawniness has already happened. So at the time of
the slaughtering of the second, it was justified, but what didn't happen
is I wasn't aware of it. So when the fact only happens
later to justify it retrospectively, you don't get off the hook. But
when the reality was there at the time but you weren't aware
of it, that's our question. Would that get you off the hook
for slaughtering the second? So let's take a look, okay? אמר ליה
לאו היינו דרבה ורבא *amar leih lav haynu de-Rabbah ve-Rava*, isn't this
the debate of Rabbah and Rava? דאיתמר D'itmar, *de-itmar*, it was said.
שמע שטבע תינוק tinok. בים *shama she-tava tinok ba-yam*, if you heard
that an infant was drowning in the ocean. There you go, Mordechai,
פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh *pikuach nefesh* case.
And on שבת Shabbos.
*Shabbat*, yes, thank you. ופרס מצודה להעלות דגים *u-faras metzuda l'haalot dagim*,
he said, "Oh, that's all very nice, but I'm hungry," and you
were casting out your net to catch fish. You were unconcerned with
this drowning infant. And what happens? והעלה דגים *ve-he'ela dagim*, and you,
first of all, you caught fish, חייב chayav, *chayav*, that's not a
חידוש *chiddush*. להעלות דגים והעלה דגים ותינוק *le-haalot dagim ve-he'ela dagim ve-tinok*,
you were trying to catch fish but up in your net came
fish and the infant. So what's happening? As far as you're concerned
in your head,
you're not trying to do anything honorable, you're not trying to save
the infant, you're just trying to catch fish. So subjectively what you're
doing is a violation, but objectively what the casting of it which
catches the infant in the process is an act of saving a
life on שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*. So do we go by subjectively what
motivated you to define
the act? But so if you did a separate act to get
the fish you were מחלל שבת. m'chalel shabbos. But if it was
the same act, if you saw me casting the net and catching
the infant, you would say, "Oh, obviously it's Rabbi Linder, he's a
צדיק, tzaddik, he's not trying to catch fish on שבת, Shabbos, and
it just happened incidentally." So that act, that physical single act would
have been totally justified. The only, right? It's not like it was
a different thing that was done. It just happened to do two
things, catch the infant and catch the fish. So do we define
the act subjectively or objectively to say whether it was a justified
חילול שבת chul Shabbos or not?
So this, isn't that the same as if you thought you were
eating meat and you ate חלב chelev or the other way around?
Well there's the גמרא Gemara obviously if you think you're doing well,
well, no, if you think you're eating חלב chelev and you're not,
then you didn't objectively do an עבירה, aveirah, although the גמרא Gemara
you're right, it's somewhat analogous, the גמרא Gemara there says that because
of your bad intentions you need a certain amount of כפרה kappara
but you didn't do a חטאת, chatas, you didn't do an עבירה.
aveirah. And if you thought you were not eating חלב chelev and
you were, then you're doing an עבירה בשוגג. aveirah b'shogeg. This is
different because here the act has two aspects to it. It has
a חילול שבת chilul Shabbos aspect, you know, it
looked at from one perspective it's justified because it's serving a שבת
shabbos. need or something that's warranted on שבת. shabbos From this perspective
it's not justified and it's all going to depend on whether we
define it based on your subjective perspective or objective. So it's different
than your case because in your case
the act is either neutral, here it's אסור assur and מותר. mutar.
Right, essentially. Right, I mean here it really had both components to
it. So this, so that was the case that was raised. רבא
אמר חייב, Rava amar chayav, רבא Rava says you're חייב, chayav. we
go by your intent. רבה אמר פטור, Rabbah amar patur, רבה Rabbah
says you're exempt, you go by the objective reality.
And so it may be the exact same issue about the scrawny
animal? No, we go further.
ועד כאן רבה לא קפטר אלא כיון דשמע אמינא נמי דעתיה אתינוק.
V'ad kan Rabbah lo ka'patar ela keivan d'shma amina nami datei atinok.
We're going to argue that even רבה Rabbah that says that you're
exempt does not just say you go by the pure objective reality,
but even the person that is most callous, you know, if he's
not, he can't just be interested in fish. You know, he's got
to also be trying to help this תינוק. tinok. So we're going
to say that deep down, no matter what you say you're thinking,
deep down you're also trying to help the תינוק. tinok, And therefore
even subjectively you're doing a מצוה. mitzvah, That's why רבה Rabbah would
say you're exempt, but not that we just go by the objective
definition. Okay, אלא, ala, one minute, לא שמע, lo shama, if you
didn't know that the infant was drowning, לא, lo, then רבה Rabbah
would not say that you had not violated. If you didn't hear
the infant was drowning and you just happened to have saved an
infant on שבת shabbos. and you were not trying and you weren't
aware, then we'll say your act was an act of חילול שבת.
chilul Shabbos.
רבא Rava says you go by your subjective, he doesn't believe that
you care deep down. Okay. So what the גמרא Gemara is saying
is like this: we have this debate of רבה Rabbah and רבא,
Rava, on the surface it looks like it's a debate about whether
we go by objectivity, whether the act was justified, but the גמרא
Gemara says no, even רבה Rabbah does not just go by objectively,
even רבה Rabbah needs you to be trying to do a מצוה,
mitzvah. but he'll just say deep down I believe you were trying
to do the מצוה. mitzvah, If that's true, applied now to our
case of the fat and skinny animal, so in this case you
were completely unaware that the first one was skinny, you had to
cut it up to find that out. So in that case everybody
would agree that the second act was a violation of שבת, shabbos.
it had not subjectively been warranted. Okay, so therefore that would be
one way of reading it. ואיכא דאמרי, V'ika d'amri, others say, אמר
ליה, he said back to him, היינו פלוגתא דרבה ורבא, hainu plugta
d'Rabbah v'Rava,
not like רבה Rabbah and רבא Rava really would agree in this
case, no, your question would exactly be debated by רבה Rabbah and
רבא. Rava. דאיתמר, we're going to say it again: שמע שטבע תינוק
בים ופרס מצודה להעלות דגים והעלה דגים חייב להעלות דגים והעלה תינוק
ודגים. Shama she-tava tinok bayam u-faras metzuda l'ha'alot dagim v'he'ela dagim chayav
l'ha'alot dagim v'he'ela tinok v'dagim.
So you tried to, so if the infant is there, you tried
to catch fish, in the end you caught the child as well.
רבה אמר פטור ורבא אמר חייב. Rabbah amar patur v'Rava amar chayav.
רבה Rabbah says exempt and רבא Rava says חייב. chayav And rather
than saying they're debating whether deep down you care about the תינוק,
tinok, we're going to make it a much cleaner debate. רבה אמר
פטור זיל בתר מעשה. Rabbah amar patur zil batar ma'aseh.
רבה Rabbah says you're exempt, you go by a person's actions and
his actions objectively you saved an infant, so it was a justified
act, we can't call this act חילול שבת. chilul Shabbos. ורבא אמר
חייב זיל בתר מחשבה. V'Rava amar chayav zil batar machshava. You go
by your intent and your intent defines the nature of the act
and therefore the act was actually a מעשה חילול שבת, ma'aseh chilul
Shabbos, not a מעשה הצלת נפשות. ma'aseh hatzalat nefashot.
Fascinating question, right, about how here do you look at something as
a מעשה מצוה ma'aseh mitzvah or מעשה עבירה? ma'aseh aveirah? Objectively it
has both components to it. Do you define it by that objectively
it had this redeeming characteristic or do you allow it to be
completely defined by the person's subjective intention? And therefore the case of
slaughtering the animal that turned out that turned out that the first
one was scrawny and I didn't know it, so the facts were
on the ground at the time of the second slaughter, so therefore
according to רבה Rabbah you go by objectively this is serving a
positive religious value, רבקה'ס Rivkah's and, you
know, concerns bracketed for the moment, and therefore it is not חילול
שבת, chilul Shabbos, it is an act that
is warranted.
Wait, so in the first case when we said before the במינו
b'minei part, when we said that you שחט shacht the כחושה kechusha
and then you... and then you... did the שמינה shmeina and רבא
Rava says you're פטור patur and even לכתחילה, lichatchila, right? So why
are you... so do you know it was כחושה kechusha, or not?
Yes. So then you should be חייב chayav for שחט shachting the
כחושה kechusha for no reason. Should have just שחט shachted the שמינה.
shmeina.
So that's a... so that's a question. You know, it's hard to
say that you're... that's an interesting point. You know, it's hard to
say חייב chayav because if you were to have brought the כחושה,
you would not have violated שבת. shabbos, You could be יוצא yotzei
your קרבן with the כחושה and you wouldn't have violated. But to
take a step back and to say if you had been paying
more attention in general you wouldn't have had to slaughter both,
you know, that's a good point.
No no, I guess meaning you had two of them there. So
did you know it was... I don't see the difference between במינו
b'minei versus what now.
The difference is that when I come to slaughter the second one,
am I aware that this is... I'm doing this because in order
to bring a better first קרבן? If I am, then I'm okay
because then the תורה Torah gives me the license to violate שבת
shabbos? to make the קרבן better. But if at that time I
don't think I'm doing a better first קרבן and I don't think
it's better, I just think like maybe I'd rather have this than
the other but I don't think it's better or I think I'm
bringing a totally different קרבן, in those types of cases within my
mind, if that were true the תורה Torah would not have warranted
me to do it. That's the difference. But your other question is
an interesting one which is why don't we say, "Hey, if you
took a step back and you would have paid attention from the
very beginning you wouldn't have slaughtered two, you would have only slaughtered
one," so why don't we at least hold you essentially חייב chayav?
for the first one? Right, right. That's an interesting question. Certainly you
could say at the time I could have brought it, but you
know why don't we sort of reassess retrospectively? I would think maybe
the answer is exactly that: the same way we don't retrospectively reassess
to get you off the hook, we're not going to retrospectively reassess
to put you on the hook. As long as at the time
you thought that this was acceptable and you only sort of realized
it after you slaughtered it. But it is a good question. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר רבה. Amar Rabba.
So רבה Rabba says, okay let's see we're today's day we're going
to fall behind but okay, חולה שאמדוהו לגרוגרת. choleh she'amduhu l'grogereis. It's
too bad that דב Dov left because here we have the case
of about שיעורים shiurim and also this also addresses מרדכי's Mordechai's questions
about, you know, פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh on שבת. shabbos So here
you have a sick person that they said he needs a גרוגרת.
grogereis. Whatever, a pressed... I keep on forgetting... fig. Thank you, a
pressed fig. Okay, he needs אחת. achas. This guy is starving to
death, whatever it is. If somebody can give him one pressed fig
we can save his life on שבת. Okay, and what happens? ורצו
עשרה בני אדם, V'ratzu asara bnei adam, just like מרדכי's Mordechai's case
about ten people get on their phone when they see this accident
on שבת, ten people all ran to go pick the nearest... well
it's not... it's funny actually because you're not going to pick a
dried fig off of a tree. But okay, it's the amount of
a dried fig but it's a fresh fig off of the tree.
Ten people ran to pick a fig off of a tree והביאו
עשרה גרוגרות v'hevi'u asara grogaros and they brought ten dried figs, or
maybe they didn't pick it off the tree maybe they did הוצאה,
hotza'ah, they carried it without an עירוב. eruv. Fine, they did הוצאה
בבת אחת, hotza'ah b'vas achas, they all showed up at the same
time. פטורין, pturin, they're all exempt because they were all trying to
save a life and therefore they're all exempt even if it turns
out that some are unnecessary. But then it goes further. אפילו בזה
אחר זה, afilu b'zeh achar zeh,
even if one guy beat the other guy and he knew it
and the second guy is unnecessary, it doesn't matter. And not only
that, אפילו קדם והבריא בראשונה. afilu kadam v'hivri barishona.
One guy was so quick that he ran, got it, gave it
to the חולה, choleh, the חולה choleh got better while the second
guy was still somewhere... he had, you know, out somewhere else trying
to find a fig and by the time he got his fig
and started carrying it the חולה choleh was already better. Nevertheless, in
his mind what he was doing was still פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh
even though objectively there was no פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh, to be
addressing anymore and therefore it's warranted. Now the key question here is,
"Did you say that he's פטור patur
or you said that he's..." No, I mean it's part of the
מצוה, mitzvah whatever. They're using פטור, patur, but even the first guy
they're using פטור. patur. I don't think פטור patur means any sense
of liability.
No, I guess meaning he thinks he's doing it for the מצוה
mitzvah and therefore he's פטור patur but we're not saying it's a
קיום מצוה. kiyum mitzvah.
Oh, that's interesting. I don't... I don't keep score. Right. Okay, right.
Okay, but here's the interesting question. What is the גרסא? girsa? Is
the גרסא אמר רבה girsa Amar Rabba or if you look at
the שיטה מקובצת Shita Mekubetzes some have the גרסא אמר רבא girsa
Amar Rava and it really matters because what did we just say
רבה Rabba said? רבה Rabba said you go by not what's in
the guy's head but what is objectively the case. That was when
what was in the guy's head was something negative, right, to try
to catch fish. Here what's in the guy's head is something positive,
to save a life. So if you have the גרסא אמר רבא
girsa Amar Rava it makes life simple. We already know that רבא
Rava goes by what's in the guy's head. So the same way
he's מחייב mechayev the guy who tried to catch the fish and
caught the תינוק, he פוטר poters the person who tried to, you
know, go ahead and carry the גרוגרות grogaros even though objectively the
person was no longer sick. The question is what about רבה? Rabba?
What would רבה Rabba say? רבה Rabba was... said that in the
first
case you're פטור. patur. Here what would he say, objectively you're not
helping the life so you're also חייב? If you have the גרסא
girsa of רבה Rabba it's very interesting and there are a couple
of possibilities. So let me tell you the possibilities. Rabba normally says
objectively in the first case by the fish you saved a life
you're פטור. patur. Here he could say I'm always going to interpret
it either way לקולא. lekula. When it comes to פיקוח נפש, pikuach
nefesh right, I'm going to say that anything that either objectively saves
a life can't be called חילול שבת chilul shabbos or anything that
was an attempt to save a life can't be called חילול שבת.
chilul shabbos. Doesn't רבה Rabba study attempt to save a life when
we said before on the fish case רבה Rabba חרז וסנפיר? chraz
v'snapir?
No, that was because no, that was when your כוונה kavana was
the opposite. Your כוונה kavana was not an attempt but objectively it
was. So רבה Rabba might be taking both positions לקולא. lekula. If
it's objectively saving a life I can't call it חילול שבת, chilul
shabbos, that was the fish case, and if it was an attempt
to save a life I can't call it חילול שבת chilul shabbos
even if by the time you were doing your חילול chilul objectively
there wasn't even a sick person left. That I think is a
very interesting position and that's basically, you know, you know, that makes
anyway sense that that should be the position that we take because
we don't want because for the sake of saving a life we
don't want people to start hesitating and saying oh maybe I shouldn't
maybe somebody else has already beaten me to it and then I'm
no longer saving a life and all of those types of things.
Obviously for the goals of saving a life you have to really
say anyway that as long as in your mind what you're still
doing is helping this person that therefore it is that therefore it
is not a חילול שבת. chilul shabbos.
But you know that's why I said to focus in on the
language of פטור patur was being used precisely to say that no
longer מצוה but you're כאילו ke'ilu like an אומר מותר omer mutar
or something, you
know?
Right, I don't think so but it's a good question. It is
an interesting question: is it just פטור patur or is it really
would you call it a מעשה of saving a life and so
forth. But what I do think is also interesting, go back to
Mordechai's point is, if it says רצו עשרה בני אדם כבת אחת,
ratzu asara bnei adam kebas achas, that what I did see was
nine other people were running and we still tell me that I
should have run as well. So in that case we don't want
anybody to hesitate. Now again in your case about picking up the
cell phone I think it's better so if everybody's trying to call
their neighbor you're there calling 911 and I'm calling הצלה Hatzalah or
they're calling 911 and I'm calling my friend the doctor, clearly that's
warranted because I might be more successful where they're not. If they're
calling 911 and they're already getting through then it's no justification for
me to pick up the phone and call 911 it's completely redundant.
But anytime there's the possibility those guys I might be successful where
those guys aren't, you go ahead and you don't hesitate and you're
מחלל שבת. And that's what this is saying here and even if
objectively it turned out what you did was not necessary at all.
Okay and I think it's important that we to read this as
רבה. Rabba. Even רבה Rabba that goes by the objective reality by
חילול שבת chilul shabbos by פיקוח נפש goes by the fact that
you think what you're doing is necessary then you go ahead and
do it and that's fine. Okay let's just read a little bit
more and at least end this topic so we start on something
new tomorrow.
What? Yeah get to the משנה. mishna. Okay.
Okay. So now we say like this: where were we? בעי רבה,
ba'ei rabba, רבה Rabba asks the following question: חולה שאמדוהו לשתי גרוגרות,
chole she'amduhu l'shtei grogros, this is more Dov's question. So they said
the sick person needs these two units worth of, this is the
case of picking something so you can't call it a dried date
fig, but anyway needs two figs let's say. ויש שתי גרוגרות בשתי
עוקצים, veyesh shtei grogros b'shnei uktzim, and there are two figs on
two separate twigs from the tree you know they're growing on separate
branch they're growing from separate locations on the branch. ושלש באוקץ אחד,
v'shalosh b'uketz echad,
and there's one twig that's holding three figs. Okay so what do
you do? Do you pick the three figs and do one act,
one act but a bigger act or two separate acts which is
less? So הי מנייהו מייתינן, hai mineihu maitinan, what do we bring
to this sick person? שתים מייתינן, shtayim maitinan, do we bring two
דחזו ליה dechazu leh that's all he really needs? או דילמא שלש
מייתינן, o dilma shalosh maitinan, or maybe bring three דקא מימעיט בקצירה
dekami'mait b'ktzira that you do fewer acts of you know picking fruit
on שבת?
Of harvesting? Instead of cutting the branch just pick the fruit? No,
no not a branch an עוקץ uketz is not a branch an
עוקץ uketz is the little twig that it stems, thank you, that's
the word, the stem they're hanging from. So when I'm going to
pluck it I do one plucking and get three or I do
two pluckings and get two.
Depends how it's growing.
Yes exactly. So
the גמרא gemara says או דילמא שלש מייתינן דקא מימעיט בקצירה. o
dilma shalosh maitinan dekami'mait b'ktzira. פשיטא דשלש מייתינן pishita d'shalosh maitinan that
you bring three. Why? That it's only one act. דעד כאן לא
קאמר רבי ישמעאל d'ad kan lo ka'amar rebbi yishmael התם hatam
until now Rabbi Ishmael did not say his position there about trying
to do three rather than five אלא דכי מימעיט באכילה קא מימעיט
בקצירה ela d'chi m'mait b'achila ka m'mait b'ktzira
when you're minimizing the amount of food you're also minimizing the amount
of harvesting. You're doing less you know harvesting if you're only doing
three instead of five. אבל הכא דכי מימעיט באכילה קא מפיש קצירה
aval hacha dechi m'mait b'achila ka mafish ktzira
here if I were try to do less quantity of food two
dates I would wind up doing more מלאכה, melacha, I would harvest
twice, I would do two pickings. ודאי שלש מייתינן vadai shalosh maitinan
we certainly do one you know three the three dates that come
through one act of picking. Now that is goes to Dov's question
about שיעורים shiurim and how do I look about שיעורים? shiurim? If
it's one act but a bigger act or a smaller act it's
still one violation. So one act of three dates is less of
a violation of שבת than two acts each one of one date.
One is one act the other is two acts. Two acts is
a bigger violation no matter what the quantity is. Dov's question... was
either the question about if I'm continuously doing something, I'm harvesting continuously,
I'm sifting continuously, I'm drinking wine and I'm a נזיר Nazir continuously.
Is that one act that's just with a big amount, or is
that multiple acts? That's where there's interesting questions about did they warn
me, did they not warn me, how do you divide it, how
do you not divide it, okay, but clearly separate—but when it's clearly
separate acts, obviously that's the bigger violation, and again רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Ishmael would rather, going back to רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Ishmael, have you
do more sifting, which is one act done but for with more
over more amount of time, than do less sifting but do multiple
acts and harvest more wheat. Okay, continued tomorrow.